<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: devise | Scott W. Bradley]]></title>
  <link href="http://scottwb.com/blog/categories/devise/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://scottwb.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-27T11:59:25-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://scottwb.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott W. Bradley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Revisited: Adding Filters to Stock Devise Controllers]]></title>
    <link href="http://scottwb.com/blog/2012/02/16/revisited-adding-filters-to-stock-devise-controllers/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-16T23:54:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://scottwb.com/blog/2012/02/16/revisited-adding-filters-to-stock-devise-controllers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Six months ago, I wrote a quick blog post about <a href="http://sleeplesscoding.blogspot.com/2011/08/adding-filters-to-stock-device.html">adding custom filters to stock Devise controllers</a> without subclassing all the Devise controllers. At the end of the post I noted that the prescribed method only worked in the production environment, and not in development.</p>

<p>Today I come to you with a solution that works in development as well as production. The basic mechanics are the same, but we'll factor it slightly differently.</p>

<p>First, we'll create a module in <code>config/initializers/devise_filters.rb</code> where we'll implement a method to add all the filters to Devise that we want. We also need to make sure this module calls this method upon initialization so that our filters get added upon startup (important for the production environment).</p>

<p>``` ruby devise_filters.rb https://gist.github.com/1851733 View Gist</p>

<h1>Put this somewhere it will get auto-loaded, like config/initializers</h1>

<p>module DeviseFilters
  def self.add_filters</p>

<pre><code># Example of adding a before_filter to all the Devise controller
# actions we care about.
[
  Devise::SessionsController,
  Devise::RegistrationsController,
  Devise::PasswordsController
].each do |controller|
  controller.before_filter :prepare_for_mobile
end

# Example of adding one selective before_filter.
Devise::RegistrationsController.before_filter :check_invite_code, :only =&gt; :new
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  self.add_filters
end
```</p>

<p>At this point, we're in the same place we left off back in August: we can add filters to Devise controller actions, but in development mode the second request reloads all the Devise classes and all our filters are gone.</p>

<p>To address this, we need to add a bit of code to the end of the initializer block in <code>config/environments/development.rb</code> like so:</p>

<p>``` ruby
MyApp::Application.configure do
  # ...the usual stuff ...</p>

<p>  # Stuff to do on each request
  config.to_prepare do</p>

<pre><code>DeviseFilters.add_filters
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>This tells Rails to call your <code>DeviseFilters.add_filters</code> method before each new request in development mode, after the classes have been reloaded.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
