<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: career | Scott W. Bradley]]></title>
  <link href="http://scottwb.com/blog/categories/career/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://scottwb.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-27T12:04:41-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://scottwb.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott W. Bradley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Joys of Working From Home]]></title>
    <link href="http://scottwb.com/blog/2012/08/15/the-joys-of-working-from-home/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-15T17:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://scottwb.com/blog/2012/08/15/the-joys-of-working-from-home</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/scottwb69/sets/72157630674264242/detail/"><img class="left" src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8022/7612882390_880e5abdc8.jpg"></a></p>

<p>I work in a team that is distributed around the country, where everyone works from their home offices. Sounds great, doesn't it? Well, it's not for everyone. First, you have to be seriously self-motivated. Personally, I get more done at home than I ever have at an office, because I get to choose when to be distracted and <em>I'm good at staying focused</em>. For some people, choosing when to be distracted is a curse. They choose to be distracted all the time. Facebook, twitter, bathroom, kitchen, twitter, kids, etc.</p>

<p>Still, some of those home distractions can plague even the most focused of us. One of the keys I've found to succesfully working from home is to have a dedicated work space. I am lucky enough to have an extra room to use as an office, and the family knows that when I'm in there, "Daddy's at work".</p>

<p>But sometimes that's not enough...</p>

<!-- MORE -->


<h3>Get Out</h3>

<p>Even when the house is empty, no co-workers are interrupting you, and you have a clear path ahead of you, the familiarity of the home office can be a distraction in itself. <em>Who's that driving down my street? I should really fix that door. I wonder if there's anything in the fridge. What time are the wife and kids coming home?</em></p>

<p>In times like these, I like to just get out and go work from somewhere else.</p>

<p>Everyone has wifi. Go to a coffee shop. Go to a pub. Go to the beach (hurray for MiFi!). Even though there is more noise and more movement, I find that sometimes just varying my surroundings can actually help me to focus. I block out the unfamiliar sounds. I expect the noise so I don't key in on every little movement. I've done some of my best out-of-the-box thinking in these kinds of environemnts.</p>

<p>This actually turns into a great perk of the distrbuted team environment. I can go work from the coffee-shop-with-a-view and it makes no difference to my co-workers. I'm still on Skype and email. I'm still checking in code and answering questions.</p>

<h3>Far Far Away</h3>

<p>So, if I can work from a coffee shop overlooking Lake Washington...what's the difference if I make it Lake Chelan? Or Miami Beach for that matter?</p>

<p>In July, I worked for 4 days from a remote part of the Olympic Peninsula. In March, to get away from the terrible Seattle weather, I worked for almost a month from South Florida. Add to that the fact that my team likes to travel to get together, and "work from home" actually becomes "work from everywhere".</p>

<p>I rather enjoy that lifestyle. The bulk of my time I'm cranking away in my home office where I am extremely productive. But every now and then, at just the right intervals, I go somewhere else to mix it up. I've even started collecting <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/scottwb69/sets/72157630674264242/detail/">photos of all these places</a>. It makes for a fun reminder of one of the reasons why I like this job and working in a distributed team.</p>

<h3>Join Me, Won't You?</h3>

<p>And now for the shameless plug. My team at <a href="http://www.validas.com/">Validas</a> is ready to grow. The beauty of this is that we can recruit from anywhere - no moving expenses. Just a generous budget to deck out your home/mobile setup with the latest tech goodies, paid internet and mobile communications, and away we go.</p>

<p>So, if you're a seasoned architect/engineer, who fits our job description and wants to thrive in this work/life style, <a href="http://www.validas.com/careers/">send us your résumé today</a>. We'd love to talk to you!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My New Home]]></title>
    <link href="http://scottwb.com/blog/2012/04/27/my-new-home/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-27T13:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://scottwb.com/blog/2012/04/27/my-new-home</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am pleased to announce that I have found my new home. As of next week, I'll be starting my new position as the VP of Engineering at <a href="http://www.validas.com/">Validas</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.validas.com/"><img class="left" src="/images/validas-logo.png" title="Validas" alt="Validas"></a></p>

<p>Over the last two months, I've networked with a lot of great people and have considered opportunties at many great companies. There are so many exciting things going on in our industry, that this was not an easy decision. After taking some time to reflect, the opportunity at Validas stood out above the rest for a number of reasons.</p>

<!-- MORE -->


<p>The biggest differentiating factors were the company culture and lifestyle, and the comaraderie and ethos of the team. Earlier this month, I spent 3 days in NYC with the core members of the team. This happened to be during a big crunch time for them, with an important ship date coming just around the corner. I got to see first-hand how the team works and plays together, and how they deal with last-minute hiccups and schedule pressure. I had the opportunity to be a fly on the wall while they worked and to be included in some very interesting architecture discussions where it was clear my expertise was immediately impactful. I even got to take part in some fun PR and marketing operations with the team. I like how this team carries itself and, of all the places I've searched, I believe this is where I will feel the most at home.</p>

<p>Our team is distributed around the country, and we collaborate using all the modern online tools. Even though it's still before my official start date, I've had a chance to get my feet wet this week just for fun (and because I am too excited to hold back). I am looking forward to enjoying the work-at-home lifestyle where I already have plenty of experience and know that I can be super-productive while still being able to hit the gym and have lunch with my kids.</p>

<p>Another big attraction to Validas is that it presents the greatest opportunity to work with cutting-edge technologies to solve the kinds of problems I find interesting. The volume of data we handle at Validas is enormous and growing rapidly. The huge success of our enterprise product, <a href="http://www.validas.com/solutions/vera-for-enterprise/">VERA</a>, shows that we're already the premier provider of big-data solutions in the mobile space ⎯ not to mention our forthcoming consumer-facing offerings. I see this as a great opportunity to lead the development of innovative solutions in big-data intelligence, to push the envelope in exicting areas such as machine learning and predictive analytics, and to build the next generation of consumer-facing products. The vision of this company and its founding team is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Hairy_Audacious_Goal">big, hairy, and audacious</a> - just the way I like it!</p>

<p>After being on the sideline for two months, I am chomping at the bit to get back into the game. I'm already ramping up. My first level of impact will involve applying my fresh perspective to existing systems to help find architectural solutions to the next wave of challenges. I'll also be heavily involved in building and launching some new products that have yet to be announced, so stay tuned...</p>

<p>Many thanks go out to everyone that supported me while I found my next path - especially my wife, Laurie. I rely on your support and your faith in me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving On]]></title>
    <link href="http://scottwb.com/blog/2012/03/06/moving-on/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-06T12:25:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://scottwb.com/blog/2012/03/06/moving-on</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I resigned my position as CTO at <a href="http://www.balassanianenterprises.com/">Balassanian Enterprises</a>.</p>

<p>Those of you who know me know that this is <em>huge</em>. I've been working closely with the founder, Edward Balassanian, for a <em>long</em> time. It's been spread over multiple companies and an array of varying products, but it's always been a shared ethos with the same core group of people that has defined that period of my career. Leaving that behind feels a bit like an emotional breakup. Such a big part of my professional and personal identity was wrapped up in how we worked together, what we built, where we've been, and our vision of the future. We put everything into it.</p>

<p>It's also a bit like leaving home to explore new worlds.</p>

<!-- MORE -->


<p>I didn't leave because of some falling out or because of "creative differences". I think Edward and the team at Balasannian Enterprises have brilliant ideas and an exciting work environment. Some of the best minds in software development, product design, intellectual property, and creative strategy work there.</p>

<p>I left because it is time for me to do something different. My motiviation has always been driven by the pursuit of <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u6XAPnuFjJc">autonomy, mastery, and purpose</a>. That hasn't changed. It's the way I've been going about it that needs to change. I feel the need for fresh inspiration, new relationships, and a different variety of opportunity.</p>

<p>How will I achieve that? I have no idea.</p>

<p>There are so many options; it's a bit daunting. I have some ideas that I might like to pursue on my own. I have some great contacts in the industry that are working on some really cool and <strong><em>BIG</em></strong> problems. It would be awesome to align with them. There are some exciting companies in my own backyard working on building the future and there is a vibrant, growing community of tech startups here in the Seattle area. I have a skill set that is in high demand on the contracting/consulting scene, and there's always the allure of contributing on a large scale to a meaningful open source project. That kind of networking can be fun and door-opening.</p>

<p>I've committed to taking at least a month off to let it all sink in. With an open mind, I am going to explore all avenues and opportunities before crafting the path into the next phase of my career. I'm open to all ideas! Please feel free to comment below or connect with me privately. I'd love to hear your feedback.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
