<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: facetdigital | Scott W. Bradley]]></title>
  <link href="http://scottwb.com/blog/categories/facetdigital/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://scottwb.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-28T11:41:49-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://scottwb.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott W. Bradley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[8 Startup Lessons in 6 Months]]></title>
    <link href="http://scottwb.com/blog/2014/05/27/8-startup-lessons-in-6-months/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-27T11:49:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://scottwb.com/blog/2014/05/27/8-startup-lessons-in-6-months</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The following is an excerpt from a <a href="http://facetdigital.com/facet-digital-first-six-months/">blog post</a> I wrote for my company, <a href="http://facetdigital.com/">Facet Digital</a>, that was published today. We've been in business for six months, and we wanted to share what we have learned so far.</em></p>

<h2>So what have we learned?</h2>

<p>Stay committed. The first six months are about grit and hustle. Keep your eye on the ball, and know when to walk away from a bad deal. Remember how valuable you really are.</p>

<p>Doing this has taught us a few key lessons that we'd like to share with our 6-month-younger selves...</p>

<!-- MORE -->


<ol>
<li><p><strong>Know what your customer needs.</strong> At first we struggled to succinctly describe what we do as a technology consulting firm. We build apps. We write code. We design things. We know how to manage projects. We handcraft delightful user experiences that...blah blah blah. Those things are not what are customers need. <em>Our customers need their problems solved.</em> You have technology problems. We solve them for you so that you can focus on your business.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Don't sacrifice quality.</strong> One of my favorite quotes as a consultant:</p>

<blockquote><p> "If you think it's expensive to hire a professional to do the job, wait until you hire an amateur." --Red Adair</p></blockquote>

<p>We've seen the reality in this time and time again. In fact, we've made a good living cleaning up after amateurs. The cost of hiring an amateur is not immediately realized. It comes back to haunt you again and again over the lifetime of your project. We don't want our names on that. When potential customers ask us to drop our rates to match some half-priced bargain firm, we politely decline. We know they'll be back when the excrement hits the proverbial whirling blades.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Never lock in a client.</strong> I never sign up for an online service that won't let me quit on a moment's notice and export all my data. Why shouldn't we give <em>our</em> customers the same benefit? In software consulting this means providing full transparency into everything we do. Written records of deliverables, wireframes, ERDs, blueprints, API docs, wiki instructions, etc. We strive to make it 100% easy to replace us, and we let our customers know this. You're never locked into us. Our clients stick with us because of the value we provide, not because we enact dubious practices to try to force them to be dependent upon us.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Work for payers. Be a payer.</strong> "<a href="http://smashingreader.com/How_do_you_persuade_someone_to_pay_for_%E2%80%9Cfree%E2%80%9D_information_i23805563">Payers value their time more than their money.</a>" Amy Hoy nails it with this simple piece. A client that will pay you for your expertise, to get the job done, while they are off solving their own bigger and better problems, is like GOLD. They value their time and will pay you to solve problems and save them time. A client that doesn't value their time will spend six hours researching the solutions to a problem <em>you're</em> hired to be the expert in. They'll impede your ability to provide them value, and they'll nickel-and-dime you to death. Run away.</p>

<p>By the same token, when running a small business, you should <em>be a payer</em>. We're way more productive and profitable when we focus on what we do best, and pay someone else to save us time and money on the rest. That's why after learning the ropes of business accounting, we hired an awesome accountant.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Invest in tools, platforms, and processes.</strong> I always take notice of a professional carpenter's tools and processes, and how those serve as multipliers for their skill. A pro has the right tools and he knows which tools to apply to which problems. Building software is no different. Small teams often try to get by only using free tools, cobbling together pieces of custom code, and trying to build everything in-house to save cash, when buying a solution would move them so much farther ahead. At Facet, we're not afraid to pay for platforms like AWS and Heroku, buy tools like Adobe Creative Cloud, and outsource commodity technology to SaaS platforms like SendGrid. Likewise, we're in a great position to identify common problems across multiple clients, and solve them with one solution that we can sell over and over again.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Give back.</strong> So much of what our industry builds today is based on the free and open-source software world. When we started Facet Digital, we gave ourselves a goal of contributing back an average of <a href="https://github.com/facetdigital">one open-source project per month</a>, no matter how big or small, and we're right on track. Not only is it rewarding to be a part of that community, it generates real leads and sparks valuable networking.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Trust your co-founders.</strong> We've all seen the stereotypical co-founder feuds. One founder manipulating the other. Bad-mouthing behind each others' backs. Countering each others' every move. Why even go into business together if that's how you're going to act? One of Facet Digital's core principles is to let each other fail and learn. We try things outside of our comfort zones. We make the bold moves, and we trust each other's motivation and intellect. If we're always worrying about each other, we're not putting our energy in the right place.</p></li>
<li><p><strong><em>Audentes fortuna iuvat.</em></strong> Fortune favors the bold. Starting a company is great exposure therapy for fear of failure. The easy, comfortable path is not fulfilling. The quickest way to stunt the growth of a fledgling company is to play it safe. Babies learn to walk by trying to stand up and falling over thousands of times. Their egos don't get hurt by failure. They just get up and keep trying. At Facet, we have a ton of bold moves on deck. Baby steps...</p></li>
</ol>


<p><strong><em><a href="http://facetdigital.com/facet-digital-first-six-months/">Read the full article at facetdigital.com</a></em></strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wake Surfing With RubyMotion]]></title>
    <link href="http://scottwb.com/blog/2014/02/09/wake-surfing-with-rubymotion/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-09T13:53:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://scottwb.com/blog/2014/02/09/wake-surfing-with-rubymotion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/supra-boats-swell-surf-system/id804765775?mt=8"><img class="left" src="/images/posts/2014-02-09-wake-surfing-with-rubymotion/swell.jpg" width="350" title="Supra Boats Swell System" alt="Supra Boats Swell System"></a></p>

<p>A couple weeks ago, our first <a href="http://facetdigital.com/">Facet Digital</a> client project to go public in 2014 was launched in the Apple App Store: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/supra-boats-swell-surf-system/id804765775?mt=8">Supra Boats Swell Surf System</a>.</p>

<p>This is a multimedia catalog app designed for reps and resellers on the boat show floor, allowing them to show off their <a href="http://supraboats.com/swell/">Swell System</a> for wake surfing. It features an interactive look at some of the unqiue features of this system, such as the ability to change the shape of the wave and even which side of the boat the wave is on! I'm no professional wake surfer, but just watching some of the videos embedded in this app make me anxious for summer to arrive...and to participate in some of these fun photo shoots with the great folks at Supra Boats for next year's app.</p>

<p><a href="http://ramsmusings.com/">Jeremy</a>, <a href="http://koolmanchu.com/">Leif</a>, and I had a blast building this app. Part of that was because the content was so cool. A bigger part was because because we decided, for the first time, to build an iOS app using 100% RubyMotion, instead of going the traditional XCode and Objective-C route.</p>

<p>So, I thought I'd share a litte bit about why we enjoyed using RubyMotion...</p>

<!-- MORE -->


<h2>7 Reasons We Liked RubyMotion</h2>

<p>Most of the code we've written in the last 5 - 10 years has been in higher-level, programmer-pleasing, dynamic languages like Ruby, Python, and JavaScript. While I do have an extensive background in C and C++, sometimes I cringe at the thought of going back there. That's what Objective-C represents to me. Sure, it has message passing like Smalltalk, and the last few years of improvements like ARC and some of the excellent static analysis tools are great, but for my programmer productivity buck, Objective-C in all its verbosity doesn't even compare to the expressiveness of Ruby.</p>

<p>Plus, I hate XCode. I'm an Emacs, Vim, and zsh guy. Keep my hands on the keyboard.</p>

<p>Here are a few of the highlights we experienced:</p>

<h3>1. The Language</h3>

<p>If you ask me, the Objective-C syntax is ugly and cumbersome. Maybe that's just the view through my Ruby-colored glasses, but just compare this simple Objective-C code:</p>

<p><code>objc
// Objective-C
UIView *view=[[UIView alloc] initWithFrame:CGRectMake(x, y, width, height)];
[view setBackgroundColor:[UIColor colorWithPatternImage:[UIImage imageNamed:@"a.png"]]];
</code></p>

<p>to the equivalent RubyMotion code:</p>

<p>```ruby</p>

<h1>ruby</h1>

<p>view = UIView.alloc.initWithFrame([[x, y], [width, height]])
view.backgroundColor = UIColor.colorWithPatternImage(UIImage.imageNamed('a.png'))
```</p>

<p>Or how about native types, list comprehension, and block syntax?</p>

<p>```objc
// Objective-C
NSMutableDictionary<em> d = [NSMutableDictionary dictionary];
for (int i = 0; i &lt; 100; ++i) {
  NSNumber </em>v = @(i);
  d[[v stringValue]] = v;
}</p>

<p>__block int sum = 0;
[d enumerateKeysAndObjectsUserBlock:<sup>(id</sup> key, id onj, BOOL *stop) {
  sum += [obj intValue];
}];
```</p>

<p>```ruby</p>

<h1>ruby</h1>

<p>d = {}
(0..100).each { |i| d[i.to_s] = i }</p>

<p>sum = d.values.inject(0) { |memo, value| memo + value }
```</p>

<p>Even though RubyMotion is compiled to LLVM just like the Objective-C code is, I am sure one could make a performance argument in favor of Objective-C in examples like this. However, I prefer to optimize for developer productivity, time to market, and ease of correctness. The beauty of RubyMotion is that you can call anything natively written in Objective-C or C anyway, so you always have the option to factor out performance sensitive pieces if you feel it is necessary.</p>

<h3>2. The Test Infrastructure</h3>

<p>If you're used to TDD in a language like Ruby, using tools like RSpec, you'll find the iOS/Objective-C ecosystem lacking in this department. RubyMotion integrates Bacon, a mini RSpec of sorts, that provides a great DSL for unit and integration testing. For example:</p>

<p>```ruby
describe "Dealer" do
  before do</p>

<pre><code>@dealer = Dealer.new(40, -100, "Cool Dealer", "http://dealer.com/")
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  it ".closest_dealer_to finds the closest dealer to a given location" do</p>

<pre><code>closest_dealer = Dealer.closest_dealer_to(
  CLLocation.alloc.initWithLatitude(
    47.7,
    longitude: -122.2
  )
)
closest_dealer.is_a?(Dealer).should == true
closest_dealer.title.should == "Active Watersports"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Running these tests is as easy as running the <code>rake spec</code> command. This builds all your app and library code, yoru test code, downloads a test executable to the simulator, runs it, and prints typical RSpec-style output right to the terminal. The build/test cycle is almost identical to what you'd do for a Ruby on Rails app. You can even run the test suite on the device with <code>rake spec:device</code> and can filter to specific test cases when you want to focus on one part of the app.</p>

<h3>3. The Workflow</h3>

<p>The workflow is all based around <code>rake</code>. Everything is done via the command line. No XCode required. For an old-school guy like me, this is way it should be. My workflow goes like this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Write code in Emacs</li>
<li>Run <code>rake spec</code> to build the test suite, download it to the simulator, and and run it, seeing the output in my terminal.</li>
<li>Run <code>rake</code> to build the app, downloaded it to the simulator, and run it.</li>
<li>Play with the app on simulator.</li>
<li>Use the REPL to tinker with layout, variables, etc. live on the simulator!</li>
<li>Repeat as necessary.</li>
<li>Run <code>rake device</code> to build the app for my target device, download it there, and run it, so I can play with it on a real iPhone or iPad.</li>
<li>Run <code>rake testflight notes="Added new features!"</code> to build an AdHoc distribution, upload it to TestFlight, and push it out to all of my beta-testers.</li>
<li>Run <code>rake archive</code> to build the whole submission to the app store.</li>
<li>Drag the <code>.ipa</code> that outputs into the Application Loader, and I'm off to the App Store!</li>
</ul>


<p>Note the part about the REPL! This is one of my favorite parts. I can't stand working in a langauge without a good REPL. It's one of the reasons I love working in Ruby and Python. Not only does RubyMotion provide a nice REPL, it is run in the context of the running app. That means you can call methods on live objects, print out their values, etc. This can come in super handy when you just want to tweak the positioning of something until you like it, and then read out its final values.</p>

<p>You can also use <code>puts</code> to print to <code>stdout</code> right there in the REPL in your terminal, like you're used to with your usual Ruby apps.</p>

<h3>4. The Integration</h3>

<p>It's very cool that out of the box, RubyMotion comes with <a href="http://testflightapp.com/">TestFlight</a> integration. That's hands-down the best way to get your pre-release app builds in the hands of beta-testers and stakeholders.</p>

<p>If you're not into Emacs (why wouldn't you be?), <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/ruby/">RubyMine</a> by JetBrains is a great IDE for RubyMotion (as well as Ruby on Rails). It integrates with auto-completion of the iOS SDK API, and the rake-based test runner too. And it has support for Emacs key-bindings. ;)</p>

<h3>5. Great Libraries</h3>

<p>You can't talk about RubyMotion without mentioning <a href="https://github.com/rubymotion/BubbleWrap">BubbleWrap</a> and <a href="https://github.com/rubymotion/sugarcube">SugarCube</a>. Both of these libraries add tremendous value and easy-of-use to RubyMotion. They provide two different perspectives on wrapping CocoaTouch/iOS APIs with more idiomatic Ruby interfaces -- with some amount of overlap. These go a long way to making your code even less verbose -- particularly when dealing with the direction one-to-one nature of calling Objective-C APIs from RubyMotion.</p>

<p>Consider SugarCube, for example:</p>

<p><code>ruby
view.on_swipe(direction: :left, fingers: 2) do |gesture|
  # handle two-finger left swipe
end
</code></p>

<p>You don't even want to know what that code looks like in raw RubyMotion, let alone Objective-C. SugarCubes adds some useful tools to the REPL as well, like the <code>tree</code> command that outputs information about your view hierarchy, and lets you gain access to these easily:</p>

<p><code>
(main)&gt; tree
  0: . UIWindow(#6e1f950: [[0.0, 0.0], [320.0, 480.0]])
  1: `-- UIView(#8b203b0: [[0.0, 20.0], [320.0, 460.0]])
  2:     +-- UIButton(#d028de0: [[10.0, 10.0], [320.0, 463.400512695312]])
</code></p>

<p>BubbleWrap provides a JSON interface that is identical to the native Ruby JSON API, making your web service consumers from your Rails apps easy to port over. It also gives us some great one-line high-level wrappers for common operations like playing a movie or taking a picture with the camera, for example:</p>

<p>```ruby</p>

<h1>Uses the rear camera</h1>

<p>BW::Device.camera.rear.picture(media_types: [:movie, :image]) do |result|
  image_view = UIImageView.alloc.initWithImage(result[:original_image])
end
```</p>

<p>Before you re-invent anything in RubyMotion...look in BubbleWrap and SugarCube first. They're open source, of course, so even if you need to customize their behavior, you can learn a lot by looking at their source code.</p>

<h3>6. Compiled Performance</h3>

<p>Unlike other non-Objective-C iOS app frameworks like Sencha Touch or PhoneGap, RubyMotion compiles to the same LLVM code that Objective-C does. It uses the same compilers. The secret is that RubyMotion is not Ruby. It is a subset of Ruby, based on MacRuby. There are a few features of Ruby that do not exist, but most of them do. This is because Objective-C and Ruby are very similar, and both attribute their message-passing and object-oriented nature to a Smalltalk heritage.</p>

<p>You can program slick animations with RubyMotion that perform as well as those made in Objective-C, without dealing with the sub-par performance of the JavaScript engine running a bloated jQuery library inside a <code>UIWebView</code>, like you would with PhoneGap.</p>

<h3>7. Memory Management</h3>

<p>Memory Management - you don't have to. The RubyMotion team has basically built their own ARC-style memory management baked into the language constructs. You use Ruby like you always do, the RubyMotion framework takes care of auto-releasing unreferenced objects, similar to Apple's ARC. You rarely need to worry about references, but in the rare case that you do (e.g., for cyclical references), the <a href="http://www.rubymotion.com/developer-center/guides/runtime/#_weak_references">WeakRef</a> class gives you what you need. The RubyMotion docs are pretty good too, and they generally point out very explicitly when you are in danger of needing to use a <code>WeakRef</code>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Developing an iOS app with RubyMotion was fast and fun. I believe programming should be fun as much as possible. Anything tedious should be automated or abstracted -- and that's exactly what RubyMotion has done for iOS programming. We'll definitely be using RubyMotion at <a href="http://facetdigital.com/">Facet Digital</a> for a few more iOS apps coming out in the next few months...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
